<story-context id="bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>4</epicId>
    <storyId>3</storyId>
    <title>Breeder Account Creation & Favorites</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-11</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/stories/4-3-breeder-account-creation-favorites.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>breeder</asA>
    <iWant>to create an account and save bulls to favorites</iWant>
    <soThat>I can track bulls of interest across browsing sessions</soThat>
    <tasks>
      - Extend User model for Breeder role (already exists in schema)
      - Create Favorite model with many-to-many relationship
      - Create breeder registration flow
      - Update login flow to support Breeder role
      - Create favorites API endpoints (GET all, POST add, DELETE remove)
      - Add favorite button to BullCard component
      - Add favorite button to bull detail page
      - Create favorites page with empty state
      - Implement guest user prompts for login
      - Add favorites count to navigation
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    AC1: Breeder account creation with Sign Up button, registration form (Name, Email, Password), role auto-set to "Breeder"
    AC2: Breeder login with email/password, session persists, name shown in navigation
    AC3: Favorite button (heart icon) on bull cards, filled/unfilled state, optimistic UI update, persists after reload
    AC4: Favorite button on bull detail page, syncs with browse page
    AC5: Favorites page shows all favorited bulls in card grid, empty state with link to browse
    AC6: Remove from favorites updates UI immediately, syncs across pages
    AC7: Guest users prompted to sign up/log in when favoriting, return to current page after login
    AC8: Favorites count badge in navigation, updates when favorites change
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/epics.md</path>
        <title>Epic 4: Bull Comparison & Favorites</title>
        <section>Story 4.3: Breeder Account Creation & Favorites</section>
        <snippet>Enable breeders to create accounts and save bulls to favorites/watchlist. Breeder role automatically assigned. Favorite state persists across sessions. Guest users prompted to login.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/architecture.md</path>
        <title>Architecture Decision - Authentication</title>
        <section>AD-2: Authentication - NextAuth.js v5</section>
        <snippet>NextAuth.js v5 configured with email/password provider, JWT sessions, bcrypt password hashing. Session data accessible in server components. Middleware protects authenticated routes.</snippet>
      </doc>
      <doc>
        <path>docs/stories/1-3-authentication-system-with-nextauthjs.md</path>
        <title>Story 1.3: Authentication System (Prerequisite)</title>
        <section>Technical Notes</section>
        <snippet>NextAuth.js configured with Credentials provider, session strategy with JWT, bcrypt password hashing. API routes: /api/auth/signin, /api/auth/signup, /api/auth/signout. Middleware protects authenticated routes.</snippet>
      </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <artifact>
        <path>prisma/schema.prisma</path>
        <kind>schema</kind>
        <symbol>User, Role, Favorite</symbol>
        <lines>18-38, 158-172</lines>
        <reason>User model already has Role enum with BREEDER option. Favorite model already exists with many-to-many relationship (User ↔ Bull). Need to verify implementation matches story requirements.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>components/BullCard.tsx</path>
        <kind>component</kind>
        <symbol>BullCard</symbol>
        <lines>1-105</lines>
        <reason>Existing bull card component needs favorite button added. Currently wrapped in Link, need to handle click events for favorite button without triggering navigation.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>auth.ts</path>
        <kind>config</kind>
        <symbol>NextAuth configuration</symbol>
        <lines>all</lines>
        <reason>NextAuth.js configuration file. Need to verify session includes user role and ID for favorites functionality.</reason>
      </artifact>
      <artifact>
        <path>app/login/page.tsx</path>
        <kind>page</kind>
        <symbol>LoginPage</symbol>
        <lines>all</lines>
        <reason>Existing login page from Epic 1. Reference for creating registration page with similar patterns and styling.</reason>
      </artifact>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <node>
        <package>next-auth</package>
        <version>^5.0.0-beta.30</version>
        <usage>Authentication with session management, useSession hook for client components</usage>
      </node>
      <node>
        <package>@auth/prisma-adapter</package>
        <version>^2.11.1</version>
        <usage>Prisma adapter for NextAuth.js session storage</usage>
      </node>
      <node>
        <package>@prisma/client</package>
        <version>^6.19.0</version>
        <usage>Database access for Favorite model operations</usage>
      </node>
      <node>
        <package>@heroicons/react</package>
        <version>^2.2.0</version>
        <usage>HeartIcon (outline and solid) for favorite button</usage>
      </node>
      <node>
        <package>bcryptjs</package>
        <version>^3.0.3</version>
        <usage>Password hashing for breeder registration</usage>
      </node>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    - User model already has Role enum with BREEDER option (no schema changes needed)
    - Favorite model already exists in schema (verify implementation)
    - Must integrate with existing NextAuth.js configuration from Epic 1
    - Session must include user ID and role for authorization
    - Favorite button must not trigger navigation when clicked on bull cards
    - Use optimistic UI updates for immediate feedback
    - Handle authentication errors gracefully
    - Guest users can browse but must login to favorite
    - Cascade delete favorites when user or bull deleted
    - Unique constraint on userId + bullId prevents duplicates
    - Follow existing authentication patterns and styling
    - Reuse BullCard component with minimal modifications
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <interface>
      <name>Favorite Model</name>
      <kind>Prisma Model</kind>
      <signature>
model Favorite {
  id        String   @id @default(cuid())
  userId    String
  bullId    String
  createdAt DateTime @default(now())
  
  user User @relation(fields: [userId], references: [id], onDelete: Cascade)
  bull Bull @relation(fields: [bullId], references: [id], onDelete: Cascade)
  
  @@unique([userId, bullId])
  @@index([userId])
  @@index([bullId])
}
      </signature>
      <path>prisma/schema.prisma</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>Favorites API - Get All</name>
      <kind>API Route</kind>
      <signature>
GET /api/favorites
Response: { favorites: Array&lt;{ id, userId, bullId, createdAt, bull: Bull }> }
Auth: Required (session)
      </signature>
      <path>app/api/favorites/route.ts</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>Favorites API - Toggle</name>
      <kind>API Route</kind>
      <signature>
POST /api/favorites/[bullId] - Add to favorites
DELETE /api/favorites/[bullId] - Remove from favorites
Auth: Required (session)
      </signature>
      <path>app/api/favorites/[bullId]/route.ts</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>FavoriteButton Component</name>
      <kind>React Component</kind>
      <signature>
interface FavoriteButtonProps {
  bullId: string;
  initialIsFavorited: boolean;
  size?: 'sm' | 'md' | 'lg';
}
export default function FavoriteButton(props: FavoriteButtonProps): JSX.Element
// Handles toggle, optimistic updates, guest user prompts
      </signature>
      <path>components/FavoriteButton.tsx</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>Registration Page</name>
      <kind>Next.js Page</kind>
      <signature>
export default function RegisterPage(): JSX.Element
// Breeder registration form with name, email, password
// Auto-assigns BREEDER role
      </signature>
      <path>app/register/page.tsx</path>
    </interface>
    <interface>
      <name>Favorites Page</name>
      <kind>Next.js Page</kind>
      <signature>
export default async function FavoritesPage(): Promise&lt;JSX.Element>
// Server component that fetches user's favorites
// Requires authentication, redirects to login if not authenticated
      </signature>
      <path>app/favorites/page.tsx</path>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      Project uses Next.js 14 with TypeScript. Testing approach not yet established. Focus on manual testing and TypeScript type safety. Test authentication flows, optimistic updates, and cascade deletes.
    </standards>
    <locations>
      No test directory currently exists. Future tests would be in:
      - __tests__/api/favorites/ for API endpoint tests
      - __tests__/components/FavoriteButton.test.tsx for component tests
      - __tests__/app/favorites/ for page tests
    </locations>
    <ideas>
      - AC1: Test breeder registration creates account with BREEDER role
      - AC2: Test breeder login succeeds, session persists, name shown in nav
      - AC3: Test favorite button on bull cards toggles state, persists after reload
      - AC4: Test favorite button on detail page syncs with browse page
      - AC5: Test favorites page shows favorited bulls, empty state displays correctly
      - AC6: Test remove from favorites updates UI immediately across all pages
      - AC7: Test guest user clicking favorite shows login prompt, returns after login
      - AC8: Test favorites count badge updates when favorites change
      - Edge case: Test duplicate favorite (unique constraint prevents)
      - Edge case: Test favoriting deleted bull (handled gracefully)
      - Edge case: Test network error during toggle (reverts optimistic update)
      - Edge case: Test rapid clicking favorite button (debounce or disable during request)
      - Edge case: Test cascade delete when user deleted
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>
